<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en">
<title type="text">Projects</title>
<generator uri="https://github.com/jekyll/jekyll">Jekyll</generator>
<link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://vekkt0r.github.io/feed.xml" />
<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://vekkt0r.github.io" />
<updated>2015-02-22T12:18:33+01:00</updated>
<id>http://vekkt0r.github.io/</id>
<author>
  <name>Adam Engström</name>
  <uri>http://vekkt0r.github.io/</uri>
  <email>adreg@megalan.org</email>
</author>


  

<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Novatouch TKL Reverse Engineering - Part 1]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://vekkt0r.github.io/articles/novatouch-tkl-reverse-engineering-part-1/" />
  <id>http://vekkt0r.github.io/articles/novatouch-tkl-reverse-engineering-part-1</id>
  <published>2015-02-13T20:42:00+01:00</published>
  <updated>2015-02-13T20:42:00+01:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Adam Engström</name>
    <uri>http://vekkt0r.github.io</uri>
    <email>adreg@megalan.org</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">
    &lt;script type=&quot;text/javascript&quot; src=&quot;http://cdn.mathjax.org/mathjax/latest/MathJax.js?config=TeX-AMS-MML_HTMLorMML&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For a long time I’ve had a fascination for reverse engineering and
modifying proprietary hardware to add new functions or work in a
different way. I have never actually done any serious reverse
engineering myself, just enjoying what other people have done and
taken advantage of the cool stuff available (who doesn’t have an old
[dd | Open]-WRT router laying around? :-)).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To begin my adventures in reversing I start with one of the simplest
devices available, a keyboard. The specific device I choose was a
&lt;a href=&quot;http://deskthority.net/wiki/Cooler_Master_NovaTouch_TKL&quot;&gt;Cooler Master Novatouch TKL&lt;/a&gt; which is a capacitive switch TKL
(ten-key-less) keyboard. Most keyboards of this type have the ability
to change the behaviour of the modifier keys with the help of DIP
switches, for example switching the &lt;code&gt;Caps Lock&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;Control&lt;/code&gt; control
keys for better reachability. The problem with this keyboard is that
no such thing is available.. Of course one could do this in software
but this will be different for each OS and may not even be possible on
computers where the user has limited permissions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This had irritated me for a while after getting the keyboard and when
browsing around the internets and reading a &lt;a href=&quot;http://imgur.com/a/CMqpt&quot;&gt;review&lt;/a&gt; of the keyboard
there was also a teardown with some internal pictures. On one of the
pictures I saw that there was a MSP430F5510 processor, this tickled my
interest because I had just played around with MSP430 processors for
evaluation on using them in my long range RF-modules for sensor
networks (should do future a post on that). It also seemed like there was
a connector looking very much like a debugging connector close to the
processor. I immediately opened up my keyboard and started probing
around with a multimeter!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/novatouch_pinout.png&quot; alt=&quot;Programming header pinout&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Correctamundo! All of the JTAG and Spy-Bi-Wire connections to the MSP
was available in the connector. I whipped out my &lt;a href=&quot;http://goodfet.sourceforge.net/&quot;&gt;GoodFET&lt;/a&gt; and crossed
my fingers hoping that the code protection would not be enabled (not
actually believing the memory would be readable). After fighting a bit
with the (very broken) FTDI driver in OS X Yosemite I saw some life
from the keyboard and the GoodFET, no code protection!? Managed to read
out the complete BSL and main flash firmware with the GoodFET without
any problems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So… What to do now? Maybe find out some more about the hardware
before diving into the firmware?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;hardware&quot;&gt;Hardware&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some quick Google searches about the chips on the bottom of the
circuit board gave an idea about how things was connected. Here are
the most interesting ones:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Symbol&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Chip&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Function&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Z1&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;SN74LV07A&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Hex buffer&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Z2&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;SN74LV07A&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Hex buffer&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Z3&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;MSP430F5510&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Microcontroller&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Z5&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;SN74LV4051A&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Analog (de)multiplexer&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Z7&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;SN74LV07A&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Analog (de)multiplexer&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Z8&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;TP1684&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Capacitive switch sense&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Z9&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;AD5258BRMZ50&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;50k digital potentiometer&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By looking at some existing &lt;a href=&quot;https://raw.githubusercontent.com/tmk/tmk_keyboard/master/keyboard/hhkb/doc/HHKB.txt&quot;&gt;information&lt;/a&gt; about Topre keyboards it was
easy to sketch out how the switch matrix probably looked.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/novatouch_matrix_sketch.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Matrix sketch&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The hardware is a little bit different from the HHKB, instead of using
a BCD decoder to select row the Novatouch uses a hex buffer. This
consumes some more IOs on the MSP but the function is the same.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By controlling the row and column with the hex buffers and analog
multiplexers the controller chooses which switch should be connected
to the proprietary Topre capacitive switch sense chip. An interesting
part is the digital potentiometer that is connected to the cap sense,
seems like it is connected between pins 3 and 6 on the cap sense chip,
unfortunately I was not able to find any data-sheet for the cap sense
so I’m not sure about it’s function. Was hoping it would be connected
to the I2C interface of the MSP so it would be easy to mess around
with but it seems to be directly routed to an unpopulated
header.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;programming-the-digital-potentiometer&quot;&gt;Programming the Digital Potentiometer&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/novatouch_pot.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Digital Potentiometer Programming&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Interested in finding out more about what the digital potentiometer was
used for I connected a BusPirate to the I2C bus of the
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.analog.com/static/imported-files/data_sheets/AD5258.pdf&quot;&gt;AD5258&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;I2C&amp;gt;[ 0x30 0 [ 0x31 r ]
I2C START BIT
WRITE: 0x30 ACK
WRITE: 0x00 ACK
I2C START BIT
WRITE: 0x31 ACK
READ: 0x15 NACK
I2C STOP BIT
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Reading RDAC register&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reading out the default value it seemed like the it was programmed to
around &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;16 k\Omega&lt;/script&gt; according to equation from data-sheet (ignoring
the fact of device specific calibration which differs up to &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\pm 30
\%&lt;/script&gt;..).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;R_{WB}(D) = \frac{D}{64} \cdot R_{AB} + 2 \cdot R_{W}&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By changing the resistance the activation point of the keys changed. A
higher resistance made the activation point get lower (the key needs
to be pressed down deeper). Lowering the resistance should then make the
activation point higher but I&#39;m not sure I noticed any change in my
highly scientific testing (holding down a key exactly above the
original activation point then reprogramming the resistance and seeing
if the keyboard starts sending any keypress).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;I2C&amp;gt;[ 0x30 0 0x34 ]
I2C START BIT
WRITE: 0x30 ACK
WRITE: 0x00 ACK
WRITE: 0x34 ACK
I2C STOP BIT
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Writing RDAC register (not persistent)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When approaching the upper limit for the resistance some keys stopped
registering presses, some of them continued to work if really
bottomed out hard. Was a bit surprised that the keys behaved so
differently across the board, could not really find any connection
between the placement of keys and which keys stopped working. Makes
one wonder how the original activation point of the keys between keys
differ.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;wrap-up&quot;&gt;Wrap-up&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/novatouch_schematic.svg&quot; alt=&quot;Novatouch schematic&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this first part of Novatouch teardown I made some analysing of the
hardware and how the key matrix looks. In the next part I will do some
analysis of the software and see how it can be modified to work more
like I want.&lt;/p&gt;


    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://vekkt0r.github.io/articles/novatouch-tkl-reverse-engineering-part-1/&quot;&gt;Novatouch TKL Reverse Engineering - Part 1&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Adam Engström at &lt;a href=&quot;http://vekkt0r.github.io&quot;&gt;Projects&lt;/a&gt; on February 13, 2015.&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
</entry>


  

<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[First Post]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://vekkt0r.github.io/articles/first-post/" />
  <id>http://vekkt0r.github.io/articles/first-post</id>
  <published>2015-01-11T13:13:00+01:00</published>
  <updated>2015-01-11T13:13:00+01:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Adam Engström</name>
    <uri>http://vekkt0r.github.io</uri>
    <email>adreg@megalan.org</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">
    &lt;p&gt;So, some years after everybody else I have finally come around to
creating a &lt;em&gt;blog&lt;/em&gt;. My intent is to write about different personal
projects, both hardware and programming related. No thought that this
will be found / read by so many people but more of a experiment to
play around with documenting my projects to gain experience in
techical writing. If somebody manages to find something interesting
then that will be a nice bonus. Probably it will end up abandoned in a
while like most peoples other blogs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some short information about myself: IAmA EE working as a consultant
with Embedded Linux kernel and application development. Some of the
areas I enjoy spending my time off on is sensor networks, reverse
engineering, home automation and other small embedded projects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The blog is setup using GitHub &lt;a href=&quot;https://pages.github.com/&quot;&gt;pages&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://jekyllbootstrap.com/&quot;&gt;Jekyll&lt;/a&gt; which for me as a
web-design-illiterate was very pleasant to setup and customize. Awesome to
be able to write and publish without leaving Emacs and the
terminal. With the existing themes it even looks acceptable (unlike
something I would have designed…).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Update 2015-02-22&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;After using default Jekyll for a while I quite soon discovered that
it was not as awesome as I first though. As soon as I started writing
and wanted to include an image I found out the stock themes were quite
bad at presenting images (no scaling, if including a huge image then
it was presented in native resolution). Looking for alternatives I
tried out some different plugins but most of them required using
special liquid tags instead of normal markdown which heavily limits
the portability of the raw posts.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;For a while I used Tom theme and changed the css file to limit the
width of &lt;code&gt;img src&lt;/code&gt; tag which kind of worked. Then I wanted to use some
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.mathjax.org/&quot;&gt;MathJax&lt;/a&gt; formulas and discovered the deployment was no longer so
smooth because plugins are not allowed by GitHub pages (totally
understandable though).&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Back to the drawing board… What I ended up with was publishing the
generated site instead of the Jekyll source on GitHub. There are many
examples of how to do this but none of them were as simple as just
pushing the code and letting GitHub handle generation. Feels like
something that should be built into Jekyll to be able to easily deploy
to servers without ability to generate.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;What I did was something like this (taken from &lt;a href=&quot;http://stackoverflow.com/questions/7539382/how-can-i-deploy-from-a-git-subdirectory&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;):&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-sh&quot;&gt;git branch -M master source
sed -i &#39;/_site/d&#39; .gitignore
git add .gitignore
git add _site/
git commit -m &quot;Add _site to vc&#39;
git push origin :master # Remove the currrent master from GitHub, had
                        # to change the default branch under the repo
                        # settings of GitHub to be able to delete
git subtree push --prefix _site origin master # Publish the contents
                                              # of _site to master branch
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Then on each change I locally run &lt;code&gt;jekyll build&lt;/code&gt; and then commit the
changes before running the subtree push again to update remote
master. This way I keep both the source and generated files in the
same repo.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://vekkt0r.github.io/articles/first-post/&quot;&gt;First Post&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Adam Engström at &lt;a href=&quot;http://vekkt0r.github.io&quot;&gt;Projects&lt;/a&gt; on January 11, 2015.&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
</entry>

</feed>